Henry Ward Beecher Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry Ward Beecher Papers 1836-1886 1840-1865
MSS12252
Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887
5,400 items
18 containers
9 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Abolitionist, author, and Congregationalist clergyman. Primarily drafts of Beecher’s sermons and a small amount of correspondence, seminary notes, notes for speeches and lectures, other writings, and miscellaneous material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887.; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887. Life of Jesus the Christ. 1891.; Jesus Christ--Biography.
Subjects
Congregational churches--Clergy.; Sermons, American.
Places
United States--Religion--19th century.
Occupations
Abolitionists.; Authors.; Clergy.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Henry Ward Beecher, abolitionist, author, and Congregationalist clergyman, were given to the Library of Congress by Anne Beecher Scoville and Maria V. Delgado between 1944 and 1952.
Transfers
A photograph album was transferred to Library of Congress Prints and Photographs Division where it is identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry Ward Beecher are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Ward Beecher (1813-1887) span the years 1836 to 1886, with the bulk of the material originating between 1840 and 1865. Included in the collection are correspondence, sermons, writings (including manuscript and galley proof of The Life of Jesus the Christ ), notes and notebooks, prints and photographs, financial papers, clippings, scrapbooks and printed matter. All of the material relates to Beecher's work as a theologian and clergyman with the greatest portion of it consisting of drafts of his sermons.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1836-1885 (Box 1)
- Lecture, 1858 (?) (Box 1)
- Speech, 1880 (Box 1)
- Writings, undated (Box 1)
- Seminary notes, 1836 (Box 1)
- Notebooks, 1843-1848 (Box 1)
- Notebook, 1838 (Box 2)
- Sermons (Box 3)
  - 1837-1841 (Box 3)
  - 1841-1843 (Box 4)
  - 1844-1850 (Box 5)
  - 1850-1852 (Box 6)
  - 1853-1854 (Box 7)
  - 1854-1855 (Box 8)
  - 1856-1857 (Box 9)
  - 1857 (Box 10)
  - 1858-1859 (Box 11)
  - 1859-1860 (Box 12)
  - 1860-1865 (Box 13)
  - 1866-1886 (Box 14)
  - Undated (Box 15)
  - Undated (Box 16)
  - Undated (Box 17)
- Financial papers (Box 18)
- Clippings (Box 18)
- Scrapbook (Box 18)
- Prints and photographs (Box 18)
- Maps (Box 18)
- Printed matter (Box 18)
- Miscellany (Box 18)